♪ [music] ♪
[people talking]
Okay. So...
-That's part of the scene
isn't it, the wind?
- Why don't you fix the scarf around him
a little bit more.
- That's gonna do it.
- What is this movie about?
I think this movie is about a personal me
that doesn't exist.
And an entangled me, which is everybody.
Your body is biological but also
a field of energy and information.
- And so, you just have this aura?
-Yes.
- I am that.
You are that.
All this is that.
That alone is.
- Can we go eat?
-Yes.
♪ [music] ♪
The basic quest always is,
"Who am I?"
"How do you define, 'I'?"
The real "I," was never born
and never dies.
It has no definition in space,
no boundaries in time.
It's eternal, it is unborn
and it does not die.
I don't think of myself
as a traditional Indian Guru,
I think of myself more
as an explorer of consciousness,
just like Edmund Hillary
was exploring Mount Everest.
Jacques Cousteau was exploring
the depths of the ocean.
- He may not think of himself
as a Guru but millions of others do.
[audience clapping]
Here's how that happened.
Born and raised in India.
Graduated medical school
head of his class.
Newly married US immigrant.
Has kids. Not around much.
Hard worker, hard partier.
Realizes, his life isn't
on the right track. Changes course.
Fringe medicine man.
- He is a poet, a prophet
of alternative medicine...
- Bestselling author.
[T.V. clips]
- Guru to the stars.
- My name is Lady Gaga
and the most influential person
in my life is Deepak Chopra.
- Sparkly glasses, red sneakers,
all of the above.
- Hi, Mister Chopra.
- None of the above.
- Doctor Chopra.
- My entire life, people have been asking
the same questions,
"What's it like to be
Deepak Chopra's son?"
"Are you spiritual like him?"
"What was it like growing up with him
as a dad?"
They don't usually ask about me,
Gotham, they ask about him, Deepak.
Sometimes I can barely tell where he ends
and I begin.
So right now, we're a few hours away
from leaving for Thailand.
Are you gonna miss me when I go?
-Yeah.
Go where?
-To Thailand.
- Oh.
- Putting together
all the camera equipment right now.
And making sure we have everything
that we need.
He's coming, too.
The only way to catch my dad is
to catch up with him.
He is being ordained as a Buddhist Monk.
The plan is rendezvous with my dad
in Bangkok.
And faithfully document the latest chapter
of the Chopra saga, it's a sure fire hit.
Logline, a guru in his twilight years
embarks on a year long journey
with his wayward son,
to discover the true identity
of something or the other.
The DVD goes in the Self Help aisle
of the book store.
Then the audio book, podcast,
of course, my dad doesn't know it yet,
but that's not the film
I'm planning on making.
I've always known that
the world's perception of my father
doesn't necessarily align with mine.
Is that really a surprise?
Does anyone see their dad as some sort
of spiritual holy man?
Thirty-six years in, I still
can't really tell you who my father is.
Does that say something about him or me?
I guess the film is the thing
where I figure it all out.
♪ [music] ♪
- What is a human being?
Why are we here?
Do we have a soul?
Does God exist?
What happens to us after we die?
These are questions that have been
asked for centuries and I think,
it's in a sense, almost arrogant of me
to suggest that I can answer
these questions,
that I can transcend to a higher truth
where I can understand my own identity.
- My father has been on the road non-stop
for most of my life.
So it's fitting we begin the story
as tourists in a strange world.
When your dad informs you of his plans
to become a monk,
don't try to make sense of it,
you just roll the cameras
and try to keep up.
- Okay, you can't just keep
filming randomly.
Dad's a monk but he apparently paid
for the souvenir shopping, photo ops,
five star hotels and all paid for
by wealthy Thai benefactor.
What do you think about spiritual silence
that starts at the Peninsula Hotel?
-I think it's a good prelude
to be comfortable
before you're uncomfortable.
For about twenty years,
I've had the romantic notion
of being ordained as a Buddhist Monk.
And I've been ready to embark
on a different plain of existence.
- Do you miss the family?
No. It's too early actually.
It's part of a much bigger story, Gotham.
You have to leave your family,
you have to leave your body,
you have to leave your mind,
you have to leave your personality,
you have to leave your children,
you have to leave your grandchildren,
you have to leave the world.
It's as if you never existed.
- Detachment from family
has been a lifelong specialty of my Dad's.
And following him down this river
feels just like growing up with him,
if you wanna find him anywhere,
if you want any sort
of engagements whatsoever,
you have to follow him into his work.
That means a lot of traveling.
Or listening to him talk for ages
on the subject of... whatever.
It also meant being raised
in front of cameras.
Being publicly groomed
to inherit the keys to the kingdom
and never getting away from the spotlight
long enough to figure out what I wanted
for myself.
- Gotham Chopra is anxious to sing
the songs his father taught him.
His father, of course, is Deepak Chopra.
- The son of privilege
has come out with a book of his own...
- I think I'll be very soon,
I'll be overshadowed by him.
- I think the character in this book
is very much an heir to something
and I think nobody knows
exactly what it is.
The truth is, I did know.
I was inheriting a personality
that wasn't my own.
Thoughts I didn't create,
books that were hardly original
and products that I didn't really buy.
- If you have weaknesses,
that doesn't make you flawed,
it makes you complete.
- In other words...
- To stay detached
and not have expectations.
I wanted to talk to the world
in my own voice.
I want you to come back, Gotham,
one day and will tell all of the secrets
about having a father who has
all of the secrets--
- That's an hour long show.
[laughter]
I wanted to use cameras
to cut through all the theory.
- Hey, Gotham.
- Hey, Crystal. Well, you know,
we've been trying to get into Chechnya
for months to cover the war...
Learn to listen,
rather than talk all the time.
- Yes, you're right...
- Yeah, that was shooting.
About three soldiers
are critically wounded.
And when I got out on my own
and saw the world unfiltered,
it was a mess.
Seemingly beyond fixing
with spiritual teachings,
I questioned what I'd been told
for so many years.
How does that happen?
I mean where does that shift in focus--?
- I think you know because I told you
when you were five years old
how that happens.
But all these years later,
I still don't get it.
And he still believes
there's a grand design to it all.
Is this part of the spiritual experience?
- I see all experience as spiritual
if you get down to it.
One of Buddha's basic tenets
is impermanence in time, which means
none of these people that you see,
or anything that you see,
these shops that you see
or the automobiles that you see,
not single one of them will be
alive in a hundred years.
- Are you ever at a loss for words?
- No, actually, I am at a loss for words
all the time because I'm trying to express
the ineffable, which is beyond expression.
This is a dream, like a wistful smoke
lost into the air.
[crowd cheering]
- Who's idea was this?
- Not mine, yours, I guess.
- Can't be all this monasteries
and monkhood and monk jobs,
it's Muai Thai.
We're in Thailand.
- It was interesting
watching the Muai Thai,
it reminded of my days
in the emergency room.
Where I couldn't get enough of gory,
blood shot people.
I couldn't wait
for the next trauma patient
to arrive so I could practice
my surgical skills.
I would enjoy the bleeding,
I hate to say it,
I would enjoy people's suffering.
[bell rings]
♪ [music] ♪
In my understanding of the world,
it's set up for maximum diversity
right here in this city, you have
maximum diversity,
from the sacred to the profane.
The so-called, "Sinners,"
to the so called, "Saints."
The divine and the diabolical.
I find that the more you embrace
the ambiguity of your existence,
the more you understand the creativity
of the universe.
- My Dad is a master
at wrapping philosophical poetry
around terrible visions
of human depravity.
That detached curiosity is the trade mark
that's made him the best-selling
inspiration to millions.
Or in the eyes of Bill O'Reilly,
in fair and bound pundits at Fox news,
an ideal target for ridicule.
- Time now for, Pinheads and Patriots.
On the Pinhead front, Deepak Chopra...
- So in the Huffington Post,
Deepak Chopra published another
Anti-American scream.
- He's blaming America.
- That's not what he was doing.
- Yes, excuse me, the exact quote was,
"He blamed America."
- Just a quick question, those glasses,
that's like from
the Elton John collection.
- What's with the holy man, wearing
the overly current eye wear?
Him showing up in those glasses,
is like, Gandhi with an ankle bracelet.
- If your son, right over here, Gotham,
was killed, all right,
by a terrorist, all right,
you're still gonna say,
"No tough interrogation, none."
- I don't believe in __.
- Like I said, detachment has been
a lifelong specialty of my Dads.
The only thing he can't seem
to totally give up
is the compulsive drive to keep talking,
traveling, writing, e-mailing
and lately, tweeting.
In my dad's version of this film,
he's left all the noise behind,
given up his Blackberry
for a silent retreat and meditation
on the true identity of Deepak.
In my version, things aren't so simple,
the noise lingers.
Five days in this city
are too much for me,
teenagers sell their bodies
in the open air markets.
The mobs yell endlessly for blood
in dank stadiums.
The arteries of the urban sprawl
are choked with traffic.
Papa sees this sweltering metropolis
as a poetic celebration
of human diversity.
I'm starting to wonder if he'll see
this film the same way.
As with everything else,
he weaves his cosmic poetry around
the frames of the film
we've begun shooting.
Right now, he wants this movie
to be a meditation
on the contradictions of life.
But the biggest contradiction
I am seeing, is in him.
The Spiritual Guru who grows restless
without his followers.
You seem more contemplative than usual.
Is it because you're not
on the Blackberry,
not Twittering,
what is about this place...
- I think the fact that I'm not on the
Blackberry, not twittering,
not on Facebook, not having to see e-mails
sometimes makes you realize
how futile all that is anyway.
If I have one flaw it's impatience.
And right now, I have nothing to do.
- In the absence of the Blackberry,
the re-tweets, Facebook updates,
notes from publishers and reminders
from his assistant,
my Dad preoccupied his time
with a new hobby,
constructing elaborate new scenes
in this film.
You already know
the ending for the film, right?
- Yeah.
- Tell it to us.
- So right this moment there are
little cells that you can hardly see.
These cells are going to your lungs,
absorbing the oxygen from the atmosphere.
Your body is performing hundreds
of thousands of activities per second.
The neurons are firing electrical storms
though synaptic networks,
which is making me possible
to speak to you.
This ground that I stand on is spinning
at about a quarter of mile per second
and it's moving around the sun at
18 and half miles per second.
I think the real me
is this endless process.
I am the photons.
I am the movement of the Earth,
I am the spiraling of the stars,
I am the universe and so are you.
And when we recognize that,
then we have conquered death
and gone beyond the illusion
of beginning and ending.
I think that should be the ending
with special effects, the Earth spinning,
moving across intergalactic space-time.
- Am I the director
or are you the director?
- Well, when I recognize that you
and I are just differentiated aspects
of the same being, it doesn't matter who
the director, who the protagonist,
who the antagonist, who the villain,
who the hero, who the choreographer is.
It's the same consciousness playing
different roles.
- Cool, then I have final prep
and we have that on tape.
- I don't think that's gonna be,
I guess.
Okay, let's go.
♪ [violin music] ♪
I was thinking actually,
the last scene being me walking
off into that forest because
this is actually very spectacular.
- Let's do it.
- Okay, rolling.
- Label me, define me, describe me,
analyze me, evaluate me.
Nail me down in a box of...
- Hey, Papa.
Which way is Burma?
- I think he's probably
gonna get there soon.
- Papa is starting to get tired
of my needling him about his addictions
to non-spiritual things.
Are you shopping?
Perhaps he knows I have no intentions
of leaving the Ritzy accommodations
out of the story. No chance of embracing
his numerous ideas for the film.
I think the story begins
about the year 1952.
Maybe he suspects that I have no plans
to turn off the camera
the next few days when inevitably
he'll get even more restless.
Yup, time to check out of the Peninsula
and into the middle of nowhere.
Oh yeah.
This is the hut where my Dad's gonna be
for his pre-ordainment
for the next few days.
I am, at the moment, thinking
about how fast I can possibly get back
to Bangkok and the Peninsula Hotel.
- It's pretty good.
It's not bad, huh?
- It's not the Peninsula.
- I like it though.
Plenty of time to be mindful of awareness.
[doorlock banging]
Soap is...
- An indulgence.
- ...is not good for the ecosystem.
- Within an hour, my Dad was on the hunt
for an indulgence that's never far
from his reach back at home.
- So, before I settle down,
I'm just wondering
if I can have a last cup of coffee.
- Oh, sure, sure, sure. I'll ask them.
But they'll let you have coffee
all the time.
- They do?
- Yeah, as long as you don't eat
heavy food.
Until then, you get coffee
and you get fruits.
- Where?
- I'll have to ask,
probably somewhere there.
- Can you please find out, just in case
I kinda freak out or something.
[laughing]
- We can hide you some canned coffee.
- I don't wanna break the rules.
I think I've had enough of indulgence.
You know, strictly speaking,
I should give up my Blackberry, too.
- You should.
- Yeah.
- Oh yeah. This is it.
- This is where I'll be.
- By now, Papa is well aware
that the cameras are rolling all the time.
And he probably knows I'm aiming
to get him with his guard down.
I also keep the cameras running
because there's nothing else to do.
But in the process, I'm starting
to notice something about us.
We follow the same script as always,
the dutiful teacher takes the floor,
the wayward student rolls his eyes.
Even as the monk handbook calls
for meditation on the moment that is now,
old rivalries boils up from the life
we supposedly left back at home.
- I'm not in the world, the world is me.
I'm not in the body, the body is me.
I'm not in the mind,
the mind is in me.
I am the creator of the mind,
the body and the world.
Now you say that to somebody like
Michael Shermer, he pulls his head out
but he has no idea
what he's talking about.
As usual, Papa's present
but not entirely.
He's still irritated about a particularly
contentious Nightline debate
that happened months ago.
- He just sort of, "Wows" people
with the language
but what does it really mean to say,
there's "Quantum consciousness?"
- When you say,
"I'm skeptical about this,"
who's the "I" that's skeptical?
Is it your network or is it you?
- And I'm not pointing this out
because I have a bone to pick with him,
I'm pointing it out
because it's the truth.
- I want you to keep that thing
with Michael Shermer
tearing his hair apart.
Nothing I enjoy more.
- Aren't you supposed to feel detached
from that right now?
- I'm not.
- It's not so much that I disapprove
of this experiment in monkhood,
but I've always seen this stark contrast
between the stoic philosopher, Deepak,
that is celebrated by the world
and the guy I know as my Dad.
The guy who turns
any mundane question
into a talking point for a new book.
- You know, less than 24 hours ago
we were at the Peninsula...
We had a nice breakfast,
we went down to the spa...
Can you talk about the contrast?
- Well, all experiences by contrast,
if you didn't know what hot was,
you wouldn't know cold.
If you didn't know what pleasure was,
you wouldn't know pain.
But that pleasure, pain, the sacred,
the profane, the divine, the diabolical,
this is the contained conflict,
which we call evolution.
In the absence of that,
life is stale, mummified, static.
[men chanting]
- The monks gives thanks for food
donated to them
by the surrounding villages.
Their newest disciples pays respect
then joins me for lunch in the commissary.
It's become clear to me that
all of this is just exotic scenery
to document the familiar patterns
of the Dad that I've known for years.
[snoring]
- He's a...meditating.
Like every son, I became frustrated
when my father thinks
he has nothing left to learn.
- I think the intellectual understanding
of some of these abbots is not as
deep as mine in all fairness
but on the other hand,
there is a certain elegance
in their simplicity
that is very attractive.
It's not getting away from it all
but getting in touch with it all.
I think once you've experienced
that kind of solitude
you can take it with you
where ever you go.
The idea of impermanence actually
allows you to go into a deeper reality.
The dream comes and goes from where?
Where does the dream arise?
Where is it conceived?
And that part is transcendent.
It's beyond space, time
and causality.
- I had this one recurring dream
when I was a kid.
I must have been about... I don't know,
6 years old.
In school, one of the other kids
called me a name, it was a racist name.
I can't remember the exact term
but I remember the feeling.
I went to my Dad, "Why do you think
he said that, papa?"
He shrugged his shoulders,
"Don't worry about it,
that boy is just expressing
his own insecurity over his identity,
he's not self aware.
He's confusing the role player
with the role underneath.
That's what most people do."
I just sort of stared at him unbelievably,
why did he say that? What did he mean?
Did he really mean it?
I think sometimes
I still stare at him that way
wondering if I do it for long enough
whether I'll ever fully understand him.
♪ [music] ♪
- So Papa, what's today?
- Today is the ordainment.
Head shaving, ride on that elephant,
the initiation of the monk.
I think most significant to me is,
"What does it mean?"
And the key is gonna make that
a lifestyle,
'cause I live in choiceless awareness,
which would be great to go
with the flow.
So, no outcomes what so ever.
No, New York Times Bestseller.
Craving, no desire to make a movie,
no desire to do this or that.
- And are you ready
to get your head shaved?
- Yeah, I need a hair cut anyway,
it's kinda getting itchy so might as well
get the head shaved
and start all over again.
- Eyebrows? Just the eyebrows?
- Whatever they want,
I mean choiceless awareness, remember?
- You've made the choice to still hang on
to your Blackberry, huh?
- I'm sending pictures home to Mom... and,
yeah, I think it's a moment worth sharing.
Impermanence is not something
to be afraid of.
It's the evolution,
it's never ending horizon.
And there's evolution of physical form,
there's evolution of the mind
and then there's evolution
of consciousness
and that should transcend
limited identities
for bigger and bigger and bigger
and ultimately for the universe.
[men chanting]
In the beginning at least.
♪ [music] ♪
- How do you feel?
- How do I feel?
I feel... a little...
strangely confused actually
because if you take away
the usual labels, then what's left?
I mean, I certainly don't look the same,
right now.
Do I feel the same?
No, I don't feel the same.
So, I'm asking myself, "Who am I?"
And I have no idea.
I'm looking forward to Krishu
being in New York
and I think I'll take him to Starbucks.
- So you still have a Starbucks craving?
I want to take Krishu to Starbucks
and buy him banana cake
because last time I took Krishu
to Starbucks and we had banana cake
he talked about it for a long time
and I want to see
the expression on his face.
- Did I give you your Blackberry back?
- Yes, you did.
Send me a text before you leave
so I know you left.
Okay, see you.
- See you in New York.
- Yeah, thank you.
♪ [music] ♪
- So how does it feel to be back
from Thailand?
- Now that I've come back,
there's definitely a subtle shift.
You know, you realize that everything
is a dream, that was a dream
and now, we are in another dream
and your audience is visiting me
in my dream right now.
The outcome is not as important
as it used to be.
Will I still look at the New York Times
Best Seller list?
Probably, but will it make a difference?
Not as it did before.
When the time is right,
whatever I'm doing,
I'll be there
and I'll be present.
- Okay, great.
- We are two minutes away
and you do know
that my son is coming
with a camera, right? He told you?
Yeah, yeah, but they'll let him in, right?
I'm launching my book,
"Muhammad: A Story
of the Last Prophet" today.
We're going to CNN now to do
The Morning Show
and then an interview with
USA Today and Tonight.
- And just like that,
we're back in the hustle.
The world of monkhood
and monastery is half a world away.
I'm not sure what to make of all that.
No time to even figure it out.
So you wanna know something
about journalists?
They want to know some of the facts,
they don't wanna know the truth.
But they're always interested
in a good story.
I need to go quickly to the bathroom,
can I?
[female reporter speaking]
I know where it is,
right here, right?
- We have two minutes
until we go live on air,
so I can catch up with my e-mails.
- Are you nervous you're about
to go on air?
- Gotham, I haven't felt nervous
since I was 14 years of age.
Okay.
- [female reporter] Good morning
live in New York, on the day
that his new book comes out, why did you
and your publisher make that choice?
- Well, thanks.
Well, there's a lot of buzz
on the internet,
on Twitter, on Facebook,
a lot of conversations going on
in places like Saudi Arabia,
it's getting a lot of attention.
The book is getting a lot of attention.
A few people are worried that in fact
it may inflame tensions, I don't think so.
- Tensions are swirling
as the 9th anniversary of 9/11 draws near.
The self help Guru, Deepak Chopra,
steps in with a fictionalized biography
of the Prophet Muhammad.
- Book sellers were nervous about that?
- Yes.
- The path of monkhood was meant to
embrace detachment,
which in my father's eyes apparently means
detachment from the controversy
around his latest publication.
The fact was things were boiling over
on CNN, NBC, ABC and of course Fox News.
- What did you say about Fox,
that we wanna...
- Fox and your self have whole heartedly
cheered on the disastrous war in Iraq.
So I can understand why you continue
to mount a rear guard--
- Deepak, I don't understand...
Wait, wait... Hang on a second.
- I'm excited all the time
to talk about anything.
- Here's the truth about growing up
chasing my Dad
through a life
of haphazardly orchestrated
speaking tours, media junkets,
public spectacle of televised debates.
When people approach him,
he knows all the appropriate humble things
to say
but the more closely I follow him,
the more I see that he's driven
by an insatiable hunger to be relevant.
And where are we going now?
- We're going to the first official launch
of "Muhhamad:
A Story of the Last Prophet".
- So what are you going to be
talking about tonight or what is the...?
- Guess what?
Jesus Christ.
[chuckles]
- Just a little about Deepak's background,
as you probably know,
he has written over 50 books,
translated into 35 languages...
[Audience applause]
There he is.
[Audience clapping]
- Thank you, again.
- So how's life?
[audience responding]
- What's up?
[audience chuckling]
First of all, thank you very much
for being here.
This is my first event with "Muhhamad:
The Story of the Last Prophet".
- How do you feel that that went?
- I think it was spectacular.
- Yeah?
- I loved it. You can feel the energy
in the room, right?
Yeah?
- We're gonna start the line right here
and if everyone, please,
in an orderly fashion,
will single file go down this side
and then we'll run the line out the door.
Everybody please single file.
- We have to keep moving, huh?
- It's clear that my Dad has settled
comfortably back into the role
that's expected of him.
And while he seems
to genuinely believe his journey
to monkhood changed him, it appears to me,
his concerns about the critical receptions
of his latest book are a present as ever.
I followed him to Thailand, curious to see
if his ordainment would truly change him,
for now, I can't really say it did.
Are we late?
- Are we late?
Every moment we are closer to death.
- You seem very impatient.
- Time is precious.
♪ [music] ♪
- City to city.
Country to country.
The blur of images begins to feel familiar
like the hazy memory
of growing up with him on the road.
You start to get lost,
unsure of where you really are.
You go to sleep in one city
and wake up in another.
- So, where are we?
- We're in Tokyo,
how many times do you ask me that?
It's obvious isn't it where we are?
Papa's receiving a prestigious
Japanese peace award.
The family's tagging along
and making a vacation out of it.
- Can you also teach me how to do Origami?
- Yes. I'm trying to figure out
how to make the elephant.
- This is familiar territory.
Bored in the Green Room.
Weird foods at awkward banquets.
I know this drill.
And now I'm making Krishu do it too.
Welcome to the world kid,
where the line
between business and family
is permanently blurry.
What do you think
the film should really be about?
What it should be about
or what I hope it's about,
I think Papa lives in a world,
in which he's the center of the universe
and everything revolves around him,
and so I think it's whether he is
on a journey to become a monk
but can't let go of his Blackberry.
I hope at the end of the film,
people take away the humanity of him
and themselves.
- He thinks it should be about
consciousness.
- Yeah, of course, because
that is his passion.
So obviously he wants a film
about consciousness.
- Papa, can you tell us where we are?
- Gotham...
- Just one question.
- We're in Tokyo, I think.
- Why?
- Family holiday.
- Well then, why are you doing your work?
- Because I have to prepare for this.
- Krishnu, what are you doing?
- Watching TV.
- What are you watching?
- Kung Fu Panda.
- He's totally kind of, in many ways,
self involved.
I think the most important
thing for him is to communicate
and to be heard.
If he didn't have an audience,
it would be a complete problem for him.
- The constant adoration of my Dad
is something the family
has gotten used to over time
but never fully comfortable with.
- She realized the importance
of your existence
and the work that you do is so amazing.
Everybody is waiting for you
and wanting your knowledge
and wisdom to be spread around the world
and she feels that so much.
- It's a wonderful place to be.
- Thank you.
- He's perfected the role
of being the object
of their devotion
becoming the teacher
everyone wants him to be but sometimes,
I sense he's doing the same thing with us.
With his grandchildren,
he's playing the role
expected but his mind is somewhere else.
[Krishnu crying]
- Rita can you say yes to
Danny DeVito's invitation... for me?
- Show Dada what type of train is this.
- Bullet.
- I love you.
- You love Dada?
- Say it's okay because Dada has
enough love for the both of you.
- Okay, let's... you know,
let's ask Gotham to use one camera
every second.
- Do you think there's a part of him now
that's more in touch
with what's important to him than before?
- He is much more at, you know,
comfortable with himself now.
Maybe when you and Mallika were small,
he was still trying to prove himself.
Now, he's proved
whatever he needs to prove.
And so that's completely taken
out of the way, so he doesn't need
to put his energy into proving himself.
- He may not need
to prove anything but I do.
For a long time, I wanted to replace
the sea of adoring faces
and constant applause with some humility.
The proverbial, "Bigger picture."
But now something’s changing,
I've turned the cameras on my own family.
Opening up our lives
to be viewed by the world.
Just as my father did before me.
How much of this story
is actually about us?
About me?
Fragments stretched over decades
about a father who wasn't there
to the Guru who was, to my trying
to reconcile what the world sees in my dad
that maybe I can't.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ My heart is on fire ♪
♪ In my madness I roam the desert ♪
♪ The flames of my passion
devour the wind and the sky ♪
♪ I try to remember in my heart ♪
♪ What I dreamt about at night ♪
♪ before I became aware
of this morning of life ♪
♪ I found my dreams... ♪
- So here we are in Sedona.
Sedona is known for Vortexes.
And of course, the plural of "Vortex"
is "Vortices" but in Sedona,
they're called "Vortexes"
and we tap into that energy
and through the guidance
and leadership of Deepak Chopra,
we weave the stillness and sounds
and we connect to nature
and we connect to this energy.
- Move with the grass. Beautiful.
Lift your face to the sky.
- In a place where people
from all over the world can tap into
this dialogue of Adanta, of consciousness,
of healing, of love, of expansion.
[audience applauding]
- So, hows life?
[audience laughing]
- What's up?
This week get into habit of "Being."
The art of being is called,"Raja Yoga."
- Do you think people grasp
a lot of what he's talking about?
I mean does a lot of he's talking about
go over their heads? Fly by people?
- You know, I think we all have had
the experience of sitting in the audience
and Deepak speaks,and you go...
- A self-image is
our personal history
which is composed of memories
of things that no longer exist.
- And then you leave,
and then you say,
"I just had the most
transformational..."
I don't know,
I can't even describe it.
Like, really?
what did he say?
Like... I don't have a clue.
- Creativity, higher guidance transcends.
Go over this many times.
This is the practice.
If you do this, this week,
along with your meditation
and everything else that we're doing--
yoga, breathing,
then actually-- thanks for coming
and go home.
[audience laughing]
[applause]
There is a phenomenon called
the "New Age."
The New Age phenomenon is looking
for the paranormal,
is looking for spirituality.
A lot of it is hype.
Maybe some of this activity
that happened here
doesn't excite me.
But on the other hand,
I'm really sensitive to people's needs,
and people have a variety of this.
- I'm living in a world
that sees itself in my father.
The reality of his life gets lost
in the picture
his audiences constructed of it.
It's as if, he actually loved doing yoga.
As if he were strict vegetarian.
As if he had time for anything
besides these 60 odd books
he's written about life.
As a young man, he did promote yoga.
He was a disciple
of Maharishi Mahesh Yogi.
He became Maharishi's protegee
and took the lead
translating Maharishi's ideas
and making them accessible
to western audience.
So, did the Beatles.
But time's changed. My Dad grew beyond
the teachings of Maharishi
because he didn't want to be
the same type of guru.
He did't want to repeat the familiar tale
of the holy men
descending from the mountain top.
Your act of recognition, devotion
and fading into obscurity.
So, rather than adopt to one code,
he adopted many.
He allowed people to use his ideas
however they wanted.
Who's he to argue with them?
- Why should we be embarrassed
about selling knowledge or wisdom?
In fact, I think the day will come
where we can already equal
the Age of Enlightenment
where the only products and services
that will be of value
will be those that empower people
have them transform,
help them enhance their self-esteem
and make them happy.
This is what we're doing.
- In his eyes,
these people are responsible
for their own happiness.
He's just the catalyst
in the form of a book,
or a workshop, or a video.
And once I looked beyond the crystals
and the scented candles
and all the things that have always
seemed kind of funny to me,
he has an ability to move people
in a way that I find admirable.
- For me, seduction of spirit
is just the ultimate.
I want this course to help me know
what my Dharma is, what is my purpose.
- He is very grounded,
and he's actually so warm
and I feel like he's a teddy bear.
I just want to keep hiding him.
[laughs]
- I just continue to be impressed
with each new book that he releases
and I think it is my crux in life
to share that with the people.
- I can honestly say I can't recall a time
when my father made me cry.
What is the root of this deep devotion?
You can trace it all back
to a singular moment in time
when Oprah Winfrey put my Dad
into the mainstream.
- I decided to invite my first guess
on the show after getting a phone call
from Michael Jackson.
He was calling to let me know
that I absolutely had to have
Dr. Deepak Chopra on the show.
- Michael convinced Oprah to listen.
Oprah convinced others to listen.
- So how evangelical are you, then?
That's really the issue.
- Not at all evangelical, please.
- How do you control
every cell in your body?
- See, because in less than a year,
you replace your entire body
down to the last atom.
Which means that right now,
what you're seeing is my 1993 model.
And the body I had last year is gone.
- Over time, his ideas started
to really take hold.
First, to the special interests,
to celebrity dabblers
then to the mainstream.
- People will spend a lifetime
become seminar junkies.
They will be able to report every book
in the world that they have read.
They will be able to write books,
and yet their life can be a mess.
♪ [music] ♪
- Michael Jackson
was an early Deepak adopter.
He loved my Dad.
Through my father, I got to know
Michael well.
We became friends, brothers almost.
I visited Neverland and got to see
firsthand the triumphs,
the torture, the tragedy,
and eventually the truth.
That my Dad who might be able
to mesmerize millions with his teachings
couldn't save some of those
closest to us.
- When we come back, we'll meet
two people including a physician
who says Dr. Chopra's technique's
cured them in advanced cancer.
Stay with us.
- Eventually, there comes a point
we have to ask,
how much of what we discover,
what we teach, what we reflect on
and document through the years,
how much of it makes a difference?
The idealism of youth never seems
to outlast time.
- So, tell me how you met.
You sought my Dad out, is that right?
- Yeah, well, I mean your Dad's
reputation preceded him.
Up until that time,there was kind
of a meditation spiritual world on one end
and a scientific world
on the other end.
Your dad helped to bring them together.
- Joining our panel is Dr. David Simon,
a neurologist who up until a year ago
thought that Dr. Chopra's methods
couldn't work.
You were a skeptic.
You are now involved actively
with Dr. Chopra, right?
- I mean we nurtured each other
by exploring various models
of what is consciousness.
And you know, that's why
it's such a paradox
that a few months ago,
I'm in New York
and I got a text from David and it says,
"Please call me."
"I have sad news for you."
So, I immediately
picked up the phone and called
because that's kind of alarming.
- I know that was. I always worry
when you give me these messages.
- So, what happened? He says,
You know, I was having
little visual defects
and I decided to go
and get a CAT scan
and I diagnosed my own brain tumor.
I have gliobastoma.
It's you know, one of those moments
you never forget in your life
because I said, of all the people, David.
I mean, we've been documenting
mind, body and soul forever
and you know, if there's anyone
who has done everything right--
this is the mystery of our existence.
- So, what do you say to people--
our audience watching TV who have cancer?
What will you say to them?
- I say that become a participant
in all alternatives
and do not, do not discount
some of the really miraculous things
that are happening in modern medicine.
[applause]
- We'd kind of joke about it,
laugh about it--
what is the meaning of death.
I think this particular conversation
should be seen by anyone who's gonna die.
- Which is everyone.
[laughs]
- It's a must-see for anyone
who's gonna die.
I mean he's got a diagnosis
but we're all on death row.
The only uncertainty is the method
of execution and the length of reprieve.
- It seems maybe a little morbid
but I'm kind of curious about it
what's my death going to be like?
Is there any sense of individuality
that's gonna prevail
or is it all goes back into Universe?
I mean I have to say that
because I've had your dad in my mind
for so long, that sometimes
I don't really know
where I end and where he begins.
- I love you, David.
- I love you too, Deepak.
I'll try to stay around with you
as long as possible.
- We're back in New York City.
Death is on my dad's mind.
Time no longer seems so abstract.
I sense in him a desperation to reach
more people with his message.
His message is changing.
No longer satisfied with New Age seminars
and red rock deserts.
Now's the time for spiritual solutions
in the real world.
- Wellness Radio
with Deepak Chopra presents
"The Road to Global
Nuclear Disarmament."
Featuring former CIA Operations Officer,
Valerie Plame Wilson,
Her Majesty, Queen Noor of Jordan,
and Lawrence Bender, producer
of "Countdown to Zero."
And now, your host, Deepak Chopra.
- You know, when I was growing up
in the 1960s,
nuclear weapons was a topic.
Everybody knew about it.
Schoolchildren were talking about it.
College students were talking
about it.
We thought at that moment
that you know,
with the great conversation
going on in the world--
the peace movement,
the anti-war movement in Vietnam,
the equality movement,
the feminist movement--
they're all kind of coming together
all at the same time.
And we thought, maybe in a few years,
we'll be living in a different world.
And despite that,
everything continued as it was.
The destruction of the environment,
racism, ethnocentricism,
extreme nationalism; more war,
more conflict.
And somehow,this whole business
with nuclear weapons
kind of slipped
from our awareness completely.
Hey, do you see that poster?
You know who that is?
That man, who's doing this?
Who is he?
- I don't know.
- His name is Puff Daddy.
You don't care, huh?
We have an amazing tendency
to kind of fall asleep.
We have to keep moving.
Okay, we can cross this.
If we manage to live through all this,
someday we'll look back
at these times as a collective psychosis
that engulfed the whole world.
[camera clicking]
- Thank you. Okay.
- This is a film about identity.
The title should be "Infinite Being."
Actually, better than "Infinite Being" is,
you know what a good title is?
Being.
- Being.
- That's it.
- Over time, I've come to appreciate
how my Dad's mind never stops racing
from one idea to the next.
His ideas for the film are as scattered
as his list of special projects.
A series of celebrity guru appearances
injecting Dad's philosophy
about quantum physics
into the mainstream.
- You're part of a matrix of information
that exists in a space time geometry
at Planck scale.
- Will society ever embrace
Planck scale geometry
the way they've embraced yoga?
I doubt it.
But I've gotta give the guy
credit for trying.
My father comes from a generation
of dreamers.
And the older he gets,
the more anxious he is
to get his message out
to as many people as he can.
For him, that now means
pure meditation workshops
with post-modern hippies
and more TV pilots
with A-list celebrities.
- People have no choice.
- This notions are becoming faster...
- The technology or the growth
or the changes that we've experienced
have done nothing to make us better.
- You know, most people think
of spiritual people like my father,
certainly Indian gurus
and they think of Ashrams,
they think of removing yourself
from the world.
But my Dad's lifestyle's kind of--
I mean, yours is you live large
but his is kind of like that, too.
He loves New York. It's his Ashram.
- He's an urban yogi.
- That doesn't-- in the scripture,
you don't want to argue
if whether he wants to go meditate.
Krishna says, "fuck that!"
You go out there
and chop their heads off.
Right now, get to work.
- Meditate.
- Get out of here.
Krishna taught Ashnu
on the battlefield.
- You are sharing with me and everybody
on this planet right now.
- That is phenomenal. I love that.
- One bread, one bread...
- Your father has turned so many keys
in so many's heads.
He is the person they look for
to be saved.
Just as any great preacher
or any great rabbi
has many followers in his congregation
who is giving light.
Where there's lots of noise,
he's trying to relieve the noise.
- Listening to Russell Simmons
wax philosophical
about inner stillness is starting
to make me feel old.
In fact the whole world seems
to be good at moving too fast
for people to keep up.
While I've been out shooting a movie,
my little boy has been growing up.
What did you say?
- Fuck!
- Soon, he'll grow beyond his toys.
- Without the co-existence
of contained conflict, there's no movie.
Right?
- And my father wants to make sure
he's listening, too.
Growing up, I played lots of video games,
but not once with my Dad.
Of course now, he's using video games
to navigate chakras,
because he wants to shape the minds
of an audience he's never reached before.
- You just use your right hand.
It's only set up for the right hand
right now.
It's interesting, this one.
If you think too much about it,
it's very hard.
But if you just sort of let it go...
- If you think about anything, it's hard
- We're here at Curious Pictures
and we've been working with Deepak
for the last 18 months on
his new video game titled "Leela."
Deepak had this idea
of basing all of the games
in the different Chakras.
We're sort of taking that
into new territory
and interweaving game and play
with traditional meditation.
- We teach our kids
very little intelligence.
We just give them information.
And I think what we have to do is
teach our kids to play in a way
in a way that activates that intelligence.
Beautiful.
- Great.
- Good job!
[chuckling]
Good stuff. I love it.
- Ironically in my Dad's world,
there's little time for reflection.
An afternoon of video game development
naturally leads into another project
he's gained affections for--
this film.
Papa and I can argue all day long
about the beginning...
- The first scene should be the woman.
- Then the ending.
- And the last scene
should be the esplanade.
- Even the title.
- You know what you should call it?
I swear to God, it's a great title.
- "Ten to the Bottom
Minus 43 Seconds."
[Gotham laughing]
I think "Ten to the Bot..."
if you have just a symbol 10,
to the Bottom Minus 43 Seconds..
- Why?
- People will say what the heck is that?
It would be intriguing, right?
- [Woman] Yeah.
- It's a very intriguing title.
- My Dad constantly dressed
to an endless stream of people
who keep his ideas alive--
artists, scientists, critics
and now me.
The last few months have become
a blur of faces,
an endless mosaic of codes
that makes up Deepak.
In his world, it all makes sense.
In past decades,
Indian gurus dressed in robes,
curled their hair
and spoke to loyal followers in Ashrams
at distant outposts on mountaintops.
Not exactly my Dad's plan.
He's become known for sparkly glasses
and red sneakers.
And his Ashram, there's something
called Deepak Homebase.
Tucked away on the second floor
of an iconic
New York city furniture store.
His followers are trendy urbanites.
And of course, the scene
is streamed across YouTube.
Here, my Dad's monkhood experience
has found its larger meaning in life,
as a great story to tell
over and over.
- I ate once a day, slept on the floor,
walked barefoot
and was in meditation 24 hours
on my death,
because that's the routine--
you meditate on impermanence
and your physical death
so you realize how precious life is.
- It sounds like hell, Deepak.
I don't know what to say.
- It was amazing.
- Okay, so I think we should start soon.
Let me find Paulette.
We have a good evening plan tonight.
- This is not Deepak Homebase.
This is Homebase
and it is about the conversation.
It's how do we change the conversation
in the world.
- Everyone watches and re-tweets
and records as always.
Tonight, I'm showing footage
from the last few months.
It was meant to decode
the great mystery of Deepak Chopra,
but so far,
has ended up just deepening it.
Papa showed no interest in seeing
any of this footage,
and he makes no qualms
about his distrust
for my method of storytelling.
- You know, I have to tell you
that Gotham was not a good student.
When Gotham speaks,
it's a different generation speaking.
- Are you always right?
- Am I always right?
I tend to think that I am.
[laughter]
So, that's the movie.
- Of course, those who think
they know Deepak are all excited.
Once again, he's met
all their expectations,
spreading his wisdom
in bite-sized elegance.
I may not have been a good student
but I'm smart enough to know
something's missing in this picture.
That I'll never fully decode my Dad
in this pieced fragments of projects,
random people and perpetual applause.
Time to leave this all behind.
♪ [music] ♪
After a year of chasing my Dad
around the world,
I brought him to the edge of it.
Back to the place where
this story really began.
India has always been
a special place for me.
Everything that I am, was or ever will be
came from here.
To complete this picture,
I needed to break the cycle.
Remove us both from the distractions
of our routines.
So Delhi train station, it's about 6 AM,
we're getting on a train to...
- Where is our luggage?
- We are surrendering to the unknown.
We trust that it will come with us.
- If you don't believe in God,
you'll have to believe over here
because only God could run this country.
♪ [music] ♪
- I bet you we have
some of our books here.
- Deepak Chopra [Hindi]
- My books are popular here, too.
- Not as popular as "The Secret."
[train honking]
- So many people, so much going on.
Like, it's as if by pure inertia,
it's moving forward
but there's no order to it.
- But in the deeper domain,
there is no distance
in either time or in space.
It's fascinating.
- Kind of a mind fog.
- Huh?
- That's a mind fog.
- It's not.
♪ [music] ♪
- Haridwar translates to Gateway to God.
In the culture of my ancestors,
tradition brings families to this city
at pivotal phases of their lives.
When you're here, the identity
of your family
is recorded into a book.
Somewhere in these narrow alleyways
lies a record of my family's history, too.
A literal code of ancestry twisting
through countless generations
of birth, life and death.
So, where are we going now?
Who are we following?
- This guy, he's gonna show us...
you know.
- Who our ancestors are?
[chuckling]
- These lanes have been like this
for thousands of years.
He's learned it, too,
the things he knows.
Not hundred percent sure though.
- The alleyways of Hardiwar
tangle into a neverending maze.
After a while, you lose yourself
in all of it--
a blur of humanity
as old as time itself.
♪ [music] ♪
- I think I've been here. Deja vu.
- In this life or...?
- He has it.
- We already tracked like six generations
and seen the handwriting in there.
Now, we could go back but then
it doesn't mean anything after a while,
who these people are.
- The language is changing.
So, there is English, Hindi, Urdu,
the addition of my son,
who has now Chinese talk
and has a Chinese middle name.
It's going to be a pretty wild turn.
- [Reading names]
You may see this and remember
your ancestors.
Sanjid, Amitav,
and your grandparents.
[Reading names].
Look at these records and go back.
And visit the playgrounds
of your ancestors.
And now, if you go back,
that scrolls all the way.
So, this is it.
- So this is what we came to find
and we found it.
A letter to Krishu.
Words feel infinitely larger
when you know your children
will see them.
How do you communicate everything
you say to them,
tell them about, warn them about?
How do you decode for them that
which has taken generations to form
in changing languages, in books,
in films?
One day in the future,
my son will walk these lanes.
He'll hear the echoes of his ancestors.
And he'll search for answers
about his father, about himself.
How important is your family to you?
My family is important.
But you know, as I'm growing older,
the only people that I'm really
attached to
is my grandchildren, right now.
You're both grown up
and you're on your own
and you know...
- Do you really think you are
changing the world?
- Me personally, no.
But the world is changing
and I'm part of what you call
a transition team,
a midwife.
- Yeah, but Papa, there's no question,
I mean, we've seen it the last few months.
We've seen it my whole life.
I mean, people are moved by you
or they follow you.
I mean, they do.
At least in their eyes,
you are changing them.
I mean, you know that.
You must sense that.
- Yeah, it did come up,
at least I have seen their lives.
And they're probably ready
to change anyway
and I happened to come along
in their life in the form of a book.
It's all kind of strange.
- There's no ego in it?
- None whatsoever.
- Yeah, right.
[chuckles]
- No, seriously none, whatsoever.
- Ahuh. Do you contemplate your death?
- Yeah, I'm very aware of my death.
I'm 64, yeah.
I mean, on the other hand,
life is unpredictable, you know.
Who would've thought that David Simon
would be having a brain cancer?
You know, he's much younger than I am.
But now looks like he might go before me.
I'm at peace with death, totally.
♪ [music] ♪
Even though I brought
Daddy's and Mommy's ashes here,
and immersed them somewhere
in one of these huts,
I want you to know that you don't
have to do that when you bring my ashes.
And I don't think Mom cares, either.
I would just, you know,
take the body to a crematorium,
wherever we are, New York or California
and throw the ashes
in the backyard or maybe...
- The Hudson.
- Maybe the Hudson or wherever.
- You don't want to be dispatched here
into the Ganges or...?
- No, it's just-- first of all,
it's a big hassle for you to do that.
I don't wanna inconvenience anyone.
And the second is, you know,
it doesn't really make a difference.
- Alright, it's a deal.
- Good. You don't have to bother
with the hassle.
♪ [music] ♪
- Someday, my father
will pass from this world.
He'll be mourned, celebrated,
commemorated and criticized.
When that time comes, I would say
I understood him as best as I could.
♪ [music] ♪
It's inevitable that his life,
his teachings, the empire he's built
and all the followers with it
will slowly drift away
down the river of time.
Yet now, I realized, he will not
really have gone anywhere.
I've been trying to break the code
that can't be found within his body.
It can't be completed in one time
or one place.
You can't find all the parts of it
in one book or one movie,
one monk, one student or one child.
Everywhere I look, I see my Dad.
He wants me to see the world
through his eyes
and every once in a while,
you know what? I actually do.
What is this movie about?
You keep asking what is it about,
what is it about?
What is it about to you?
- Yeah, I think the basic quest
always is, "Who am I?"
How do you define I?
When you die, who dies?
When you say, "Who's calling?"
I say, "It's I, Deepak."
I think the real question is,
who are you asking the question of?
Who am I? Who am I? Where do I exist?
Where's the boundary
between me and that abyss?
Where do I begin and where do I end?
Did I begin with the Big Bang?
Or when my parents
looked at each other
and fell in love?
Or when I was conceived,
or I was born?
If you go inside my body
with a surgical scalpel,
or a CAT scan or an MRI,
you won't find me there,
because I'm not there.
Where's the I
that really exists everywhere?
Is not the sun, and this light
and this atmosphere
as vital to my existence
as my heart, liver and bone?
Times Square is in me.
India is in me.
You are in me.
The whole Universe is in me.
You are a relationship.
We are all a relationship.
We are inseparably interconnected.
Our souls are entangled,
we're part of a matrix
in that entanglement
which is not only across space
but across time.
Do we have a soul?
Does God exist?
Does God exist.
What happens to us after we die?
I think what we've seen
in the last few months
is a journey across time.
There is definitely some continuity there.
You know, our minds
are part theirs.
In a sense, we're all a mirror
of each other.
You and I are just
differentiated aspects of the same being.
We are the same being
in different disguises.
The real "I" was never born
and doesn't die
and it's not your personal,
physical body or even your personality.
It has no definition in space,
no boundaries in time.
It's eternal, it is unborn
and it does not die.
- We're done?
- Done.
I've said what I need to say
and I did it well, so I'm happy.
♪ [music] ♪